NORTHERN LANDS, RUINS OF THE KING'S TOMB
（北方诸国 零落王墓）
Eighteen of you have passed the first stage of the exam.
在场18位考生 第一阶段的考试都已经合格
First of all, congratulations on passing.
首先先恭喜各位通过第一阶段
I've been told that there is all sorts of
我听说关于我过往
speculation going around
负责监考的考试结果 有各种流言传得满天纷飞
I'm sure some of you have heard of the rumors.
相信你们当中应该也有人听过
But there is no need to be nervous.
但你们无须紧张
The exam is very simple.
考试很简单
Those aiming to become a first-class mage
既然以成为一级魔法使为目标
should be able to pass it with ease.
应该能够轻松通过考试
Now then,
那么
here are the details of the second stage.
我来说明第二阶段考试的规则
ORIGINAL STORY BY KANEHITO YAMADA / TSUKASA ABE
（原作：山田钟人 作画：阿部司）
The second stage will be a dungeon raid.
第二阶段就是攻略迷宫
I will have you raid the Ruins of the King's Tomb.
你们必须要攻略这个迷宫
There is only one condition to pass.
考试合格的条件只有一个
It's to reach the deepest chamber of the Ruins of the King's Tomb.
就是抵达零落王墓最深处的房间
I am a pacifist.
我是个和平主义者
So I don't like fighting.
不喜欢争斗
Therefore, all of those who reach the goal will pass the exam.
因此只要抵达那个房间的人通通合格
Wait a minute.
等等
Many adventurers have entered here and not come out alive.
很多进去这里的冒险者都是有去无回
It's an uncharted dungeon.
这可是无人破解的迷宫啊
Do you not want anyone to pass again?
你又打算不让任何人合格了吗？
What are you saying?
你在说什么？
All of you are aiming to become the highest rank of mages.
你们都打算成为最高阶的魔法使
First-class mages make the impossible possible.
一级魔法使能化不可能为可能
Whether it is uncharted or unprecedented,
不管是没破解或是无人去过的迷宫
you must conquer it and move forward.
你们都必须要能克服万难 继续前进
How are we supposed to prove that we made it
我们要怎么证明自己
to the deepest chamber?
抵达了最深处的房间？
Should we bring back some sort of treasure?
只要带回金银财宝就好了吗？
You do not have to prove it.
完全不用证明
I will go down there too.
因为我也会一起进去
Of course, I won't help any of the examinees.
当然 我不会出手帮助任何考生
One more thing. I will give each of you this bottle.
还有一件事 我会给每个人发一个这个瓶子
It's an evacuation golem developed by
这是一级魔法使莱尔恩所开发的
the first-class mage Lernen.
撤离用的魔像
When you break the bottle, a golem will appear
打破这个瓶子 就会出现魔像
and carry you out of the dungeon.
把你带离迷宫
It's still a prototype, but it's safe enough.
虽然还在试验阶段 也已经够安全了
If used, the user will be disqualified,
一旦用了这个 就立即判定该生不合格
but don't hesitate to use it if you are wounded and cannot continue with the exam.
但是万一受伤了 或无法继续考试时 请马上使用
Letting up-and-coming mages die here is not permissible.
绝不能让大有可为的魔法使 就这样死在这里
Also, at dawn tomorrow,
还有明天的破晓时分
the bottle will break automatically.
瓶子也会自动破掉
That's the time limit for the second stage.
那就是第二阶段考试的期限
Well then, the exam begins now.
那么考试现在开始
There are multiple entrances.
有好几个入口
It seems to be a dungeon from the Unified Dynasty era.
看来应该是统一王朝时期的迷宫
Dungeons from that era have multiple entrances,
那个时代的迷宫都会有很多个入口
but all of them lead to the innermost depths.
全部都能通往迷宫最深处
If we examine each entrance,
检查每个入口
we will get a gist of its inner workings to some extent.
应该就能大致了解内部结构
We can all split up and--
那就大家分头…
Why are you talking as if we're all going to cooperate?
怎么说得好像我们要合作一样？
There is nothing to fight over in this stage of the exam.
这回考试并没有需要斗争的地方
It's better for all of us to work together.
全员分工合作会更好
That's not possible.
那是不可能的
Unlike the first stage, our teammates
跟第一阶段不同 我们的队友
don't have to be alive to pass.
不用活着也能合格
Even if we band together, there's no obligation to help each other
就算组队好了 也没有义务互相帮忙
and there's even a risk of becoming a sacrificial pawn.
甚至还有惨遭牺牲的风险
Especially since you seem to be knowledgeable in dungeons.
尤其是跟你这种 看起来很了解迷宫的人更是如此
I'm going alone.
我自己去就好
Well, the first stage sure complicated our relationships.
没办法 毕竟有先前考试的心结
It'll be hard to team up with people you don't know.
很难去跟不认识的人组队
Let's go.
走吧
Hey, wait.
等等我啊
Idiots.
真是愚蠢
How do they not see the advantages of cooperating?
怎么都不懂合作的好处呢？
Let's go, Fern.
走吧 菲伦
Are you sure, Mistress Frieren?
这样好吗 芙莉莲大人？
We can't cooperate.
不可能合作的
It's not possible anymore.
那是无法成立的
Well then, I will follow you two.
那我就跟着你们俩吧
I believe you two will be the safest ones to follow to the innermost depths.
感觉跟着你们最能安全地抵达最深处
Don't get in our way.
麻烦不要碍事喔
I will not get in your way nor help you.
不会的 我不妨碍也不会帮忙
This is the safest route.
这是最安全的路线
Let's move forward with caution while mapping it out.
一边做地图 一边小心前进吧
The floor right there
那块地板…
is a trap, so be careful.
是陷阱 要小心喔
As always, you are so knowledgeable about dungeons.
您还是一如既往地熟悉迷宫呢
I wasn't always like this though.
我以前也不是这样的
Himmel liked dungeons.
只是辛美尔很喜欢迷宫
So we did a lot of dungeon raids and took down monsters.
我们因为讨伐魔物的委托需要 攻克了很多迷宫
He liked dungeons? What do you mean by that?
很喜欢迷宫？是怎么一回事啊？
Exactly what it sounds like.
就如字面意义说的
According to him, they're exciting.
他觉得迷宫让人很兴奋
It's baffling, isn't it?
很莫名其妙吧？
These stairs lead to the next level.
走这段楼梯可以前往下一层
I see. I guess this was the wrong route.
这样啊 看来这不是正确路线
Let's go back to that fork from earlier.
我们回去刚刚的交叉路口吧
Let's do that.
说得没错
But why?
为什么？
Our goal is to find the monster in the deepest chamber.
我们的目标 是找到位于最深处房间中的魔物
When will you learn, Eisen?
你什么时候才会懂啊 艾泽？
In dungeons, you have to explore every corner of a level
迷宫就是要 每一层每个角落都去探索
before moving on to the next.
才能前往下一层啊
That's common sense among adventurers.
这可是身为冒险者的常识
No, it's not.
才没有那种常识呢
You must be thinking, "How foolish."
你一定是觉得我很蠢吧
If you can have fun while helping others,
帮助别人时 自己也能从中得到乐趣
isn't that the best?
那不是最棒了吗？
You can't be like this forever.
一直这样可不行啊
Dungeons will become more dangerous down the road.
随着越来越深入 迷宫也会越来越危险
That's right.
就是说啊
I'll have fun until the end.
那就享受到最后吧
I'll enjoy my adventures, explore dungeons,
我要享受冒险、探索迷宫
defeat monsters, find treasures,
打败魔物、找到宝物
and realize later that I've saved the world.
回过神才明白自己拯救了世界
That's the kind of journey I wish for.
那就是我期望的旅程
Plus…
再说…
that fork may lead to a rare grimoire.
那条岔路 说不定能找到稀有的魔导书呢
What are you doing? Let's hurry up and go back.
你还在拖什么？赶快回头啊
What…
什么…
It's really baffling, isn't it?
真的是很莫名其妙吧？
Kanne, let's go.
康涅 走吧
In the end, only five stayed behind.
结果最后只剩下五个人
If we all cooperated and divided up the work, it would've been
如果能全员分工合作的话
more than possible to successfully raid the dungeon.
就更有可能成功攻略迷宫了
We had enough talented people to make that possible.
本来有实力的人是足够的
Denken, not everybody can think logically like you.
邓肯 不是每个人 想事情都跟你一样有逻辑啊
Remember what you said at the end of the first stage?
还记得你第一阶段考试 结束时说了什么吗？
They're just irritated, that's all.
他们就只是不接受罢了
The smarter ones stayed behind.
留下来的人都是更聪明的人
Just think of it that way.
这么想就好了
At least we don't have any
至少我们这群人里没有
stupid people who would fall for a simple trap like a mimic and slow us down.
会掉进宝箱怪那种低级陷阱的笨蛋啊
Isn't that good enough, Denken?
这样不就够了吗 邓肯？
Someone as stupid as that wouldn't be taking this exam.
这种考试会有那么笨的人来参加吗？
Let's go.
走吧
This mana…
这股魔力…
It might be a grimoire.
应该是魔导书
Mistress Frieren, didn't you see the results from Mikheit?
芙莉莲大人 您看到 宝箱判别魔法的结果了吧？
It's a mimic.
那是宝箱怪喔
Fern,
菲伦
the accuracy rate for that spell is 99%.
那个魔法的准确率为99%
What are you trying to say?
那有什么问题吗？
Many historic discoveries
史上的重大发现
were made because of great mages who
都是因为有伟大的魔法使
saw through the remaining 1%.
看穿了那1%的错误喔
As I expected.
果然如此
There is a precious grimoire in here.
里面有珍贵的魔导书
My experience as a mage is telling me so.
我作为魔法使的经验是这么告诉我的
It's dark! I'm scared!
好黑啊 好可怕啊！
So dark! So scary!
真的好黑啊 真的好可怕啊！
Maybe I chose the wrong people to follow.
我是不是选错队了啊？
Don't step on the floor in the middle.
不要走中间的地板
The ceiling will come falling down.
不然天花板会掉下来
Don't tell me that stain shaped like a human is…
难道说那个像人的污渍是…
How brutal. It doesn't even leave behind any bones?
真是残酷 连骨头都不剩吗？
They're gargoyles!
是石像鬼！
Denken, one person got trapped inside.
邓肯 有一个人被困在里面
I know.
我知道
She's behind that wall.
她就在那道墙后面
Stand back.
你们先退后
It didn't work, huh?
果然没有用吗？
We've no choice. Break the bottle!
没办法了 打破瓶子吧！
Wow…
好厉害
One person is out of the game already.
这下已经有一个人出局了
Letting your guard down for a second can kill you.
稍有不慎就会送命
So this is the Ruins of the King's Tomb, huh?
这就是零落王墓啊
Hey, Fern. Hang on a minute.
喂 菲伦 听我说句话
Can you stop pulling for a second? I'm going to tear apart.
可以先不要往外拉吗？ 我会被撕成两半的
Okay.
好
In these situations,
这种情况
you actually have to push.
其实反而应该要往里面推
Then the mimic will gag and stop biting.
这样宝箱怪会想吐 就不会咬我了
What is it, a dog?
所以它是像狗一样吗？
You saved me.
得救了
My goodness…
真是的
How were you getting by when you were alone?
您一个人的时候是怎么处理的？
I would make it explode from inside using offensive magic.
从里面使用攻击魔法进行爆破
But I don't like doing that because my hair gets fried.
但是那样我的头发会乱掉 所以我并不喜欢那么做
I'm back.
我回来了
My hair turned into ringlets…
我变成罗马卷了…
So that's the reason why your hairstyle
原来这就是您时不时
would change from time to time?
会改变发型的原因啊？
Why?
为什么？
All right, back to business.
好 回归正传
Let's continue our raid.
继续攻略迷宫吧
They're gargoyles.
是石像鬼
Let's take them down before they move.
在它们动起来之前先干掉它们吧
This medal
这种勋章
is all over the place.
到处都有呢
Apparently, some dilettante is collecting these.
据说有收藏家在收集这种东西喔
This seems like the correct route, so let's go back.
看来这条就是正确路线 先回头吧
Why?
为什么？
It's going surprisingly smoothly.
出乎意料地非常顺利呢
Yeah, that's strange for an uncharted dungeon.
是啊 以一个无人破解的迷宫而言 也太奇怪了
Especially since we should be near the deepest chamber by now.
尤其现在我们应该 已经很靠近最深处的房间了
Either way, we can't let our guard down.
不管怎么样 都不能掉以轻心
Let's take a break once we find the next burial chamber.
找到下一个墓室时就休息一下吧
I found some great items.
找到了很棒的东西呢
They look like useless junk to me.
在我看来就是一堆破铜烂铁啊
Hmm…
奇怪…
I don't understand.
我不懂
I know, right?
是吧？
Why do those things make her so happy?
那些东西怎么能让她这么高兴？
She's rubbing her cheek against it…
居然还用脸去蹭…
Fern, you are the one I can't understand.
菲伦 我看不懂的人是你喔
I've never seen a mage as skilled as you at your age.
我从未见过你这个年纪 却如此优秀的魔法使
I'm sure you went through intense training.
想必你一定是经过相当大量的修练
But I don't detect any passion or obsession from you.
但从你身上 却感觉不到一丝热情或执念
You're a strange girl.
真是不可思议
I became a full-fledged mage in order to repay
我之所以成为独当一面的魔法使
the kindness of a certain person.
是为了报答某个人的恩情
At the time, it was my goal in life.
那时候 这就是我的人生目标
I gave it my all.
因此我拚尽全力
I never even thought about what I would do after that.
我从没想过达成目标之后要做什么
I probably
很可能那个时候
used up all of my passion
热情跟执念
and obsession during that time.
就已经耗尽了吧
Then why do you
那么为什么
continue to explore magic?
你还继续探究魔法呢？
Doesn't Mistress Frieren look like she's having fun?
芙莉莲大人看起来不是很开心吗？
She does.
确实如此
The first time I explored a dungeon,
我第一次探索迷宫的时候
Mistress Frieren was collecting magical items that looked like junk
芙莉莲大人就在收集 看起来像垃圾一样的魔法道具
and was smiling so happily.
脸上满是开心的笑容
I couldn't help but smile too.
我自己也忍不住笑了出来
I think
我想正是因为
I am pursuing magic with Mistress Frieren
我喜欢看到芙莉莲大人开心的样子
because I like seeing her like that.
我才会跟她一起追求魔法吧
I think it's time to move on.
差不多也该出发了
I made the right choice in following you two, after all.
选择跟着你们走果然是对的
I am sure you two
相信你们俩
will be able to have fun in this merciless dungeon.
在这个无情的迷宫里也能享受到乐趣
The atmosphere has changed.
氛围不一样了
We might be near the innermost depths.
应该已经到了最深处了
Wirbel.
维亚贝鲁
What? You can't walk anymore--
干嘛？走不动了…
I'm restrained.
我被封住行动了
There are three mages who are hiding their mana.
有三名隐藏魔力的魔法使
We were ambushed.
是偷袭
Really?
是吗？
Scharf, block their vision.
夏鲁夫 遮住他们的视线
The spell they used on Ehre is Sorganeil.
他们用在艾露身上的魔法 是目光束缚魔法
I know.
我知道了
No wonder the Ruin of the King‘s Tomb was impregnable.
难怪零落王墓至今无人能破
Who knew we'd run into something like this?
谁能料到居然有这种东西？
Scharf, you target me. Ehre, you target Scharf.
夏鲁夫 你对付我 艾露 你对付夏鲁夫
I will attack Ehre.
而艾露就交给我
We'll get past this.
准备突破
It's a clone made from magic.
是魔法制作的复制体
A demon or a monster must be behind this.
一定是魔族或魔物的杰作
But I've never seen anyone clone another being so perfectly.
但老朽从未见过如此完美的复制体
It had the same level of mana and skill as Laufen.
它拥有跟拉奥芬一样的魔力跟能力
It even copied her behavior.
连行为都相同
It's possible that they even took advantage of her memories.
可能连记忆都被利用了
That's a bit unsettling.
感觉真是不舒服
The only good thing about it
唯一能庆幸的一点是
is that you can tell that it's fake at first glance.
第一眼就能看出它是个冒牌货
At least we don't have to worry about friendly fire.
至少不必担心自相残杀
If the user of this spell
如果施展这个魔法的人
can manipulate multiple clones at the same time,
可以同时操控数个复制体的话
it could be very dangerous.
那就会非常危险
Either way, it was a good idea that we banded together.
不管怎么说 组队行动果然是好主意
We have more options when dealing with these.
有更多方法能对付这种东西
Denken, is that something you can deal with?
邓肯 那个你也能对付得了吗？
There's one thing I can say for certain.
只有一点老朽敢说
If this weren't an exam, I would've already broken my bottle.
要不是这是考试 老朽早就摔碎瓶子了
All right…
那么…
-It's time to call it quits. -You smell nice.
-时间差不多了 -好好闻
-If we're equally skilled, -What shall we do?
-如果实力相当的话 -该怎么办？
-winning or losing -That's not funny.
-输赢 -这可不好笑
-is up to fate. -Look at my eyes.
-就交给命运吧 -看着我的眼睛
-It's not impossible? -How much time do you need?
-不可能吗？ -需要多少时间？
"A Perfect Replica."
完美的复制体
Subtitle translation by: Kiko Morita
字幕翻译：洪贞韵